Finding Aid for Michael Ranville papers, 1953-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael Ranville papers 1953-2008
Ranville, Michael, 1943-
2009144 Aa 2, UAl
Author and political consultant from Charlotte, Michigan who wrote a book on the Milo Radulovich Case; records include interviews, correspondence, newspaper clippings, Radulovich military records, research notes, and documentation relating to the writing and publication of To Strike at a King: The Turning Point in the McCarthy Witch-Hunt.
3.5 linear feet in 4 boxes
2 oversize items
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Michael Ranville (donor no. 10211 ) in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Michael Ranville (born December 3, 1943), is author of the book To Strike at a King: The Turning Point in the McCarthy Witch Hunt. He is a native of Flint, Michigan and a former political consultant. Ranville received his bachelor's degree from Central Michigan University before joining the United States Air Force in 1966. He served in the Air Force until 1970, where he provided air-to-ground communication to the President of the United States and other high-ranking American officials from Andrews Air Force Base.
Following his time in the Air Force, Ranville returned to school to earn a master's degree in communications at Central Michigan University. He then began a career in public relations and free-lance speechwriting. In 1976, he accepted a research and speech writing position in the Michigan State Senate. Eventually, Ranville left this position to join the lobbying firm Karoub Associates.
Ranville has authored a number of magazine and newspapers articles dealing with history, politics, sports, and public relations, however, he is probably best known for his book To Strike at a King about Milo Radulovich.
Milo John Radulovich (October 28, 1926 -- November 19, 2007) was an American citizen (born in Detroit) of Montenegrin descent who served as a lieutenant in the Air Force reserve in the 1950s. In 1953, the Air Force accused him of being a security risk for maintaining a "close and continuing relationship" with his father and sister who had been identified as possible "security risks." The Air Force stripped him of his commission under the provisions of Air Force Regulation 35-62. Radulovich was eventually reinstated, but only after Edward R. Murrow brought Radulovich's case to the nation's attention on the television news program "See It Now" on October 20, 1953.
The collection consists of six series: Milo Radulovich Research materials, Writing and Publicity, Later Milo Radulovich materials, Other articles, Video materials, Sound materials, and Posters. The collection's strength lies in Ranville's interviews with Milo, his sister, and other's involved in Radulovich's Air Force Security Hearing, as well as in the other accumulated research materials.
Subjects:
Cronkite, Walter.; Friendly, Fred W.; Good night, and good luck (Motion picture); McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957--Influence.; Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.; Ranville, Michael, 1943-; Ranville, Michael, 1943---To strike at a king.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Good night, and good luck (Motion picture); Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.; Ranville, Michael, 1943-
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Radulovich, Milo, 1926-2007.; Ranville, Michael, 1943-
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Friendly, Fred W.; Young, Coleman A.
Genre Terms:
Compact discs.; Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Milo Radulovich Research materials
  The Milo Radulovich Research materials series documents Ranville's research for his book. The series contains interviews, newspaper clippings, correspondence, photocopies of Radulovich's military records, and Ranville's research notes.
  - Interviews 1992-1995
    - Walter Cronkite undated (Box 1)
    - Margaret (Radulovich) Fishman 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Vera Layton (Floyd) 1994 (Box 1)
    - Fred and Ruth Friendly 1993 (Box 1)
    - Ernest Goodman undated (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich undated (Box 1)
    - Ron Rothstein 1994 (Box 1)
    - Kenneth Sanborn 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Nancy Tuttle 1994 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, largely photocopies
    - Korean War (Box 1)
    - Joe McCarthy 1953 (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich
      - 1953-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
        (includes retrospective articles about the Radulovich case)
    - Victor Harris 1953 (Box 1)
    - Charles Lockwood 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Red Scare
      - 1953 (Box 1)
      - 1990s (Box 1)
        (includes retrospective articles about McCarthyism)
    - Miscellaneous 1953 (Box 1)
    - Serbian Publications 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Charles Lockwood undated (Box 1)
    - Hugh McDiarmid 1993 (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Radulovich Family 1950s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Michael Ranville 1992-1996 (Box 1)
    - Kenneth Sanborn 1953 (Box 1)
    - Harold E. Talbott 1953 (Box 1)
  - Military Records, photocopies
    - Transcript of the Hearing of Lt. Milo Radulovich 1953 (Box 1)
    - Air Force Letters and Memos 1953 (Box 1)
    - Board of Findings 1953 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Military Records 1953 (Box 1)
    - FBI Documents 1953 (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich Retirement Benefits 1996 (Box 1)
  - Research Notes
    - Background Information (Box 1)
    - Father Charles Coughlin (Box 1)
    - Senator Homer Ferguson (Box 1)
    - Margaret (Radulovich) Fishman (Box 1)
    - Fred Friendly (Box 1)
    - Charles Lockwood (Box 1)
    - General Timeline (Box 1)
    - Edward R. Murrow (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich Background (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich Hearing (Box 1)
    - George Sokolsky (Box 1)
    - Harold E. Talbott (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1)
  - Michigan History Article
    - "The Case Against Milo Radulovich" 1995 (Box 1)
    - Notes and Research (Box 1)
    - Article drafts (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1995 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Research Materials
    - "See It Now" 1953 (Box 1)
    - Statement by Margaret (Radulovich) Fishman 1953 (Box 1)
    - House Un-American Activities Hearings 1934 (Box 1)
    - Milo Radulovich Poem (Box 1)
- Writing and Publicity
  The Writing and Publicity series documents Ranville's writing and editing process as well as publicity efforts for his book. It contains drafts of various chapters, copyediting documents, correspondence, and publicity materials. The publicity materials mostly include correspondence, book reviews, and publicity materials related to Ranville's interviews, lectures, and book signings.
  - Drafts
    - Dust Jacket (Box 2)
    - Forward (Box 2)
    - Preface (Box 2)
    - Introduction (Box 2)
    - Prologue (Box 2)
    - Chapter 1 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 2 (Box 2)
    - Chapter 3 (Box 2)
    - Narrative Outline (Box 2)
    - Index (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Photograph Permissions Correspondence 1996 (Box 2)
  - Editing Documents
    - Correspondence 1995-1997 (Box 2)
    - Dustjacket (Box 2)
    - Outline (Box 2)
    - Index (Box 2)
    - Corrections to text (Box 2)
    - Galleys, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Publicity
    - Correspondence 1995-2005 (Box 2)
    - Book Reviews 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Author Interview Requests (Box 2)
    - Promotional Forms (Box 2)
    - Book Signings (Box 2)
    - Contact and Distribution Lists (Box 2)
    - Lectures (Box 2)
    - Articles citing Ranville 2003-2007 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Promotional Materials (Box 2)
    - Golden Age of Television Conference 1997 (Box 2)
- Later Milo Radulovich materials
  The Later Milo Radulovich materials series documents some of the publicity surrounding the film "Good Night, and Good Luck," and efforts to honor Radulovich from the mid-1990s to 2008. It contains copies of screenplays for the film, newspaper and magazine publicity, and materials involving efforts to honor Radulovich, including documents related to the posthumous Bachelor of Arts ceremony at the Bentley Historical Library in 2008.
  - "Good Night, and Good Luck"
    - Screenplay 2005 (Box 2)
    - Good night, and good luck: The Screenplay and History Behind the Landmark Movie, 2006 (Box 2)
    - "Good Night, and Good Luck" Publicity 2005 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Posthumous Bachelor of Arts Ceremony for Milo Radulovich 2008 (Box 2)
    - "The Legacy of the Milo Radulovich Case," State Bar of Michigan 1998 (Box 2)
    - Rights to Milo Radulovich's Life Story 2002-2005 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1998-2004 (Box 2)
- Other articles
  The Other articles series contains two articles written by Michael Ranville that are unrelated to Milo Radulovich.
  - The Closer, 2 items (Box 2)
- Videotapes, VHS cassettes
  The Video materials series contains a series of video cassettes related to Milo Radulovich and McCarthyism. Most of the cassettes pertain to Ranville's research for To Strike at a King, including a copy of the episode of "See It Now" that highlighted Radulovich's case. The series also contains cassettes of Ranville's speeches and interviews after publication of the book.
  - Milo Radulovich
    - Milo Radulovich, Judge Kenneth Sanborn & Michael Ranville Guests of Alan Sanborn Michigan Senate Chamber 2003 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 1)
    - An Evening with Milo Radulovich and Michael Ranville 1997 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 2)
    - 26th Michigan Legal Milestones (Box 3)
      (includes interviews with Milo Radulovich and Michael Ranville)
      (tape nos. 3-4)
    - "See It Now" October 20, 1953 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 5)
    - "See It Now" October 23, 1953 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 6)
  - Edward R. Murrow
    - Ed Murrow/American Masters 1990 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 7)
    - Murrow -- Civil Rights Newsreels to News (Box 3)
      (tape no. 8)
    - Edward R. Murrow: The McCarthy Years with Walter Cronkite (Box 3)
      (tape no. 9)
    - Edward R. Murrow (Box 3)
      (tape no. 10)
    - "Murrow US-ML" (Box 3)
      (tape no. 11)
    - Biography -- Murrow with Walter Cronkite (Box 3)
      (tape no. 12)
  - Michael Ranville
    - Book Brunch: Michael Ranville "To Strike at a King: The Milo Radulovich Story" 1997 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 13)
    - John H. Faulk Conference 1997, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 3)
      (tape nos. 14-15)
  - McCarthyism
    - Epidemic of Fear 1995 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 16)
    - McCarthy: Death of a Witch Hunter (Box 3)
      (tape no. 17)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Interviews (Box 3)
      (tape no. 18)
    - Charlie Rose and George Clooney 2003 (Box 3)
      (tape no. 19)
    - Jack Perkins (Box 3)
      (tape no 20)
    - Walter Cronkite (Box 3)
      (tape no. 21)
- Sound materials, sound cassettes except where noted
  The Sound materials series contains audio recordings of the interviews Ranville completed as part of his research. There are also cassette tapes of "See It Now," and interviews with Ranville.
  - Interviews
    - Margaret (Radulovich) Fishman, 5 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      (tape nos. 1-5)
    - Fred and Ruth Friendly, 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      (tape nos. 6-7)
    - Ernest Goodman (Box 4)
    - Irving Kempner, DAT cassette (Box 4)
    - Irving Kempner (Box 4)
    - Charles P. Lockwood (Box 4)
      (tape no.11)
    - Harry Lunn (Box 4)
    - Milo Radulovich, 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      (tape nos.13-14)
    - Radulovich Family, 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      (tape nos. 15-16)
    - Ron Rothstein (Box 4)
    - Kenneth Sanborn (Box 4)
    - Nancy Tuttle (Box 4)
    - Joe Wershba (Box 4)
      (tape no. 20)
    - Coleman Young (Box 4)
  - Edward R. Murrow Recordings
    - "A Reporter Remembers the War Years", 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      (tape nos. 22-23)
    - Combined Reel: "This is Edward R. Murrow" and "See It Now" October 20, 1953 (Box 4)
      (tape no. 24)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Ranville Interview with Ted Heusel (Box 4)
      (tape no.25)
    - "The Jack Lessenberry Show", 1 optical disks CD (Box 4)
- Posters
  The Posters series contains two posters for the film "Good Night, And Good Luck."
  - "Good Night, and Good Luck" Movie Posters, 2 items (Folder 1)